YEAR 1976
AÑO 1976
Are you crying?
¿Estás llorando?
I got a letter from a friend.
Me ha escrito una amiga.
She's a close friend of mine.
Es una buena amiga mía.
When I was 15, we tried to cross the Czechoslovakia border together.
Con 15 años, intentamos cruzar la frontera checoslovaca juntas.
But she was captured and taken to Prague.
A ella la cogieron y se la llevaron a Praga.
She says she's doing well.
Me dice que está bien.
She's a true friend who knows me better than even my parents or siblings.
Es una amiga de verdad.
With government censorship,
Con la censura que hay,
who knows what she had to do just to get this letter to me.
a saber lo que tendría que hacer para enviarme la carta.
She wrote, "If you have the time to see me, then come meet me here
Me dice: "Si tienes tiempo, ven a verme aquí,
at the sign of the Three Frogs near Cedok Bridge."
en la señal de las tres ranas, cerca del puente Čedok".
I wish I could return to Prague.
Ojalá pudiera volver a Praga.
Margot…
Margot.
-Say… -Yes?
- Una cosa. - ¿Sí?
Call me by my real name.
Llámame por mi nombre.
Just for today, I want you to call me by my real name.
Solo hoy. Llámame por mi nombre de verdad.
My name is Helenka Nováková.
Me llamo Helenka Nováková.
Just for today, I'm not Margot Langer.
Hoy no soy Margot Langer.
I sold my Reiserberger Pharmaceutical shares at just the right time.
Vendí las acciones de Reiserberger en el mejor momento.
I hit it big when I bought a little Kneuter Research stock.
Lo mejor fue cuando compré unas cuantas acciones de Kneuter.
So I wanted to celebrate a little.
Por eso quise celebrarlo.
-So you had a drink? -Just a tiny one.
- ¿Y bebiste? - Muy poco.
You're unbelievable!
Esto es increíble.
It was only one drink.
Fue solo una copa.
How many times do I have to tell you? For an alcoholic,
¿Cuántas veces tengo que decírtelo?
I see that you haven't been attending the AA group I told you about either.
Tampoco has ido a las reuniones de Alcohólicos Anónimos.
By the way, doctor, you can keep a secret, right?
Por cierto, doctor, ¿puedo contarle un secreto?
You see, there's a woman I'd like you to start seeing.
Me gustaría que tratara a una mujer.
Do you have another lover?
¿Tiene otra amante?
You see, she's a terrible alcoholic.
Bueno, es que es muy alcohólica.
She's waiting outside. Can you speak to her for a sec?
Está fuera esperando. ¿Puede ir a verla un momento?
I don't take drop-in patients.
No atiendo sin cita previa.
Get an appointment for her.
Pídale una cita.
But it's just for a few minutes.
¡Si solo serán unos minutos!
I have a house call after this and they're a very important client.
Tengo una visita después con un cliente importante.
I went to Prague in the Czech Republic.
Fui a Praga, a República Checa.
It really is a nice place.
Es un sitio precioso.
This is the fantastic Gothic cathedral in Prague Castle.
Esta es la maravillosa catedral gótica del Castillo de Praga.
Here's the square in the old town all lit up at night.
Y aquí está la plaza de la ciudad antigua toda iluminada.
It was like a town out of a fairytale.
La ciudad parecía sacada de un cuento.
What about Cedok Bridge?
¿Y el puente Čedok?
Did you go to Cedok Bridge?
¿Fue al puente Čedok?
Of course. Just like you asked me to.
Por supuesto. Hice lo que me pidió.
I found the Three Frogs as well.
También encontré Las tres ranas.
Was the woman there?
¿Y vio allí a la mujer?
No. There was nobody there.
No, no había nadie.
To be honest, I didn't find out anything by going there.
Si le soy sincero, fui allí y no descubrí nada.
Of course, I couldn't find Tenma, Nina, or Dieter either.
Y tampoco pude encontrar a Tenma, a Nina o a Dieter.
Take this.
Toma.
It's a rabbit's foot. It gives good luck.
Es la pata de un conejo.
Margot… I mean, Helenka, I…
Margot…
Thank you.
Gracias.
PRAGUE, 1980
PRAGA
THREE FROGS
LAS TRES RANAS
Yes?
¿Sí?
Excuse me.
Perdón.
I've come here from Germany looking for a woman who's gone missing.
Vengo de Alemania. Busco a una mujer que ha desaparecido.
Do you know a woman named Margot Langer? I mean Helenka Nováková.
¿Conoce a una mujer llamada Margot Langer? Perdón, se llama Helenka Nováková.
Helenka?
¿Helenka?
Incidentally, Mr. Schuwald,
Por cierto, señor Schuwald,
you haven't been eating much lately again.
que últimamente usted no está comiendo bien.
Your experience in the fire at Munich University
El incendio en la Universidad de Múnich
was both horrifying and traumatic.
fue una experiencia traumática y espantosa.
I can understand why you're not over your fear of it.
Entiendo que todavía no lo haya superado.
But you still have…
Por suerte, cuenta con…
that magnificent son of yours, Karl.
la ayuda de su increíble hijo, Karl.
There's no need to worry any longer.
Ya no tiene de qué preocuparse.
You need to eat properly.
Tiene que comer bien.
That monster…
Ese monstruo…
As long as that monster exists, I just…
Mientras ese monstruo exista, no…
How did that monster know so much about Margot Langer?
¿Por qué sabe ese monstruo tantas cosas de Margot Langer?
He knew far more than even me or Margot's son, Karl.
Sabía mucho más que yo o que su hijo, Karl.
Margot had a close friend in Prague who knew her better than her own family.
Margot tenía una buena amiga en Praga que la conocía mejor que su familia.
She exchanged letters with that woman.
Se enviaban cartas.
Around 1980, you went in search of Margot who had gone missing.
En 1980, usted fue a buscar a Margot porque había desaparecido.
In your search, you went to Prague and met that woman, didn't you?
Fue hasta Praga y conoció a esa mujer, ¿verdad?
Yes.
Sí.
I thought that woman may have been in contact with Margot.
Pensaba que esa mujer seguiría en contacto con Margot.
However, she knew nothing.
En cualquier caso, ella no sabía nada.
We spoke about our memories of Margot for a while in her doorway.
Estuvimos hablando un rato en la puerta de nuestros recuerdos con Margot.
At that time, they were there listening to our conversation.
Ellos ya estaban ahí y escucharon nuestra conversación.
Who was?
¿Quiénes?
They listened very carefully from behind the woman…
Se ponían detrás de ella
those twins.
Los gemelos.
Come in.
Adelante.
Have a seat there.
Siéntese.
Mr. Thalbach referred you to me.
Viene recomendada por el señor Thalbach.
He said you can't quit drinking either. Anyway, sit back and relax.
Usted tampoco puede dejar de beber. Siéntese y relájese.
Let's start with a little small talk.
Empecemos con una pequeña toma de contacto.
-Doctor! -What's wrong, Meredith?
- ¡Doctor! - ¿Qué pasa, Meredith?
-I'm in the middle of a counseling-- -He's on TV!
- Estoy en una sesión. - ¡Está en la tele!
Dr. Tenma's on TV!
El doctor Tenma está en la tele.
Excuse me for a moment.
Espere un momento.
Again, in top news, the suspect in the poisoning deaths of three doctors
Últimas noticias. El sospechoso de envenenar a tres médicos
at the Eisler Memorial Hospital in Düsseldorf, Germany,
en el Hospital Eisler Memorial de Düsseldorf, en Alemania,
and the murders of the journalist, Maurer, and the Fortners in Heidelberg,
de los asesinatos del periodista Maurer y de los Fortner en Heidelberg,
as well as the random killing at Heidelberg Castle,
además de el del Castillo de Heidelberg,
Kenzo Tenma, a Japanese doctor, who was hiding from police in Prague,
Kenzo Tenma, un médico japonés que huía de la policía en Praga,
was arrested on the afternoon of the fifth by Czech Police.
ha sido arrestado por la policía checa.
We currently have no further information,
Todavía no tenemos más información
so we're waiting for the police to report on how his arrest…
y estamos esperando alguna declaración de la policía.
Tenma…
Tenma.
You can't come in here. This is the office area.
No puede entrar en esta sala.
Please wait in the waiting area, Ms. Eva Heinemann!
Espere en la sala de espera, señora Heinemann.
Kenzo…
Kenzo.
So sorry I'm late, everyone.
Os pido disculpas por llegar tarde.
Playing with my grandchildren has made me younger.
Mis nietos me han rejuvenecido.
Good. I'm in my last year at university now.
Bien. Estoy en el último año de universidad.
I hear you're pretty busy yourself, Mr. Kiefer.
Señor Kieter, me han dicho que anda muy liado.
I can't believe I'm friends with a screenwriter who's going to Hollywood.
No me creo que estemos con un guionista de Hollywood.
I can't help bragging about it.
No dejo de alardear.
I just happened to catch the eye of a Hollywood producer. That's all.
Un productor de Hollywood se ha fijado en mí, nada más.
But it's given me lots of ideas for all kinds of new stories.
Me ha dado muchas ideas para un montón de historias nuevas.
That's great to hear!
¡Cuánto me alegro!
It's thanks to that operation…
Y todo gracias a esa operación.
If that brain surgery I had back then hadn't succeeded,
Si la operación de cerebro no hubiera salido bien,
I wouldn't be here.
no estaría aquí.
I wouldn't have been able to take walks with my grandkids through the park.
No podría dar paseos con mis nietos por el parque.
That's the table…
Esa era la mesa.
He always sat there alone enjoying his tea.
Ahí se sentaba siempre solo a tomarse su té.
There were other cafes where all the other doctors gathered,
Los otros médicos iban a otros cafés,
but he would come to this little cafe near Eisler Memorial Hospital.
pero él venía a este pequeño café cerca del Eisler Memorial.
When we patients came in…
Si venía algún paciente…
He'd look up at us from there…
Nos miraba desde allí…
And smile and wave.
Nos sonreía y nos saludaba con la mano.
He was such a kind doctor.
Era un médico muy amable.
Yes, he was.
Pues sí.
There's absolutely no way that kind doctor would do anything like this!
Es absolutamente imposible que pueda hacer algo así.
This is why I called you all here.
Por eso os he llamado a todos.
Many previous patients of Dr. Tenma
Hay muchos pacientes del doctor Tenma
who couldn't come today feel the same way.
que no han podido venir y se sienten igual que nosotros.
Dr. Schumann, we need you!
Dr. Schumann, le necesitamos.
Old Mr. Merkel has collapsed!
El señor Merkel se ha desmayado.
Got it. I'll be right there.
Vale, ya voy.
But first I've got to take care of something else. Wait there a second.
Necesito que tú te ocupes de algo. Espera un momento.
Sure thing.
¡Vale!
There's no way Dr. Tenma did such things!
Es imposible que el doctor Tenma hiciera algo así.
Calm down and let him talk, Mom!
Tranquila, mamá. Deja que hable.
You need to hurry up and go to him, honey!
Tienes que ir con él, cariño.
Yes, I know, but Petra, I can't--
Lo sé, Petra, pero no puedo…
Don't you give me any "buts"!
No me vengas con peros.
Dr. Tenma's been arrested for crimes that he didn't commit!
Han detenido al doctor Tenma por error.
If it hadn't been for him, I wouldn't be alive anymore.
De no ser por él, yo no estaría viva.
are you saying you won't help the man who saved your wife's life?
¿no vas a ayudar al hombre que salvó a tu mujer?
-What will happen to this village? -Huh?
- ¿Y qué pasa con el pueblo? - ¿Eh?
I'm the only doctor in this village.
Soy el único médico del pueblo.
If I leave, what will everyone in this town do?
Si me voy, ¿qué hará el resto del pueblo?
Enough of your grumbling!
¡Deja de quejarte!
You know you want to go! So get going and help Tenma!
Sabes que tienes que ir. Venga, ¡vete a ayudar a Tenma!
A doctor cannot leave his patients.
Un médico no puede dejar a sus pacientes.
Dr. Tenma would do the same.
El doctor Tenma haría lo mismo.
Doctor, hurry up and see us!
Doctora, atiéndanos rápido.
Be patient! I'm still getting ready.
Esperen, que estoy preparándome.
-How long do we have to wait? -Quit complaining!
- ¿Cuánto tiempo hay que esperar? - No se queje.
The doctor's been studying at a proper med school lately,
La doctora está sacándose la carrera
as well as running this place, even though she ain't licensed!
mientras lleva este sitio, aunque no tenga título.
Once you are in the darkness, you just sink deeper into it.
Una vez entras en la oscuridad, te acabas perdiendo en ella.
Keep your light shining.
No dejes de brillar.
I know you can become a doctor.
Te dedicarás a esto.
You'll make a fine doctor for sure.
Serás una buena médica, seguro.
Dr. Tenma…
Doctor Tenma…
Okay, I'll start seeing you now.
Vale, podéis ir pasando.
Whoever's first, get in here.
Que entre el primero.
-Get my lawyer. -Yes, sir.
- Llama a mi abogado. - Sí.
But we still don't know where Tenma will be sent to in Germany.
Todavía no sabemos
Find the best criminal lawyers out there.
Busca los mejores abogados criminalistas.
-Yes, sir. -He's the only man…
- De acuerdo. - Él es el único…
I have the feeling he's the only man who can do this.
Tengo la sensación de que él es el único.
He's the only one who can eliminate that monster.
Es el único que puede acabar con ese monstruo.
We need as many allies as possible.
Cuantos más aliados, mejor.
Let's contact all of Dr. Tenma's former patients.
Vamos a contactar a antiguos pacientes suyos.
Even though we can't do much individually, by working together, we can do a lot.
No podremos hacer mucho por separado, pero, si trabajamos juntos, sí.
I've got an idea!
Tengo una idea.
Let's get Eisler Memorial Hospital to help us set up a relief society!
Vamos al Eisler Memorial para montar un grupo de apoyo.
That'll never work.
Eso nunca funciona.
There's no way Eisler Memorial Hospital will ever agree to do that.
El Hospital Eisler Memorial nunca apoyaría esa iniciativa.
I've been listening to you. What you've said has been very touching.
Les he estado escuchando. Lo que dicen es bastante conmovedor.
But think about it realistically.
Hay que ser realistas.
How can you possibly prove Tenma's innocence?
¿Cómo van a demostrar la inocencia de Tenma?
Dr. Becker…
Doctor Becker.
I mean, he's got plenty of motive, but he's got no alibi.
A ver, es que tiene muchos motivos y no tiene coartada.
They said they've got actual physical evidence, you know.
Dicen que incluso tienen pruebas físicas reales.
Sure, you can get a bunch of people together and make a fuss,
Está claro que pueden unirse y armar jaleo,
but no matter how competent the lawyer you hire is,
pero, por más bueno que sea el abogado que contraten,
It's a pity though. He was such a gifted doctor.
Es una pena, porque era un médico con mucho talento.
It is a pity.
Qué lástima.
Let me ask you one more time.
Se lo preguntaré otra vez.
Just exactly what is your connection with Tenma?
¿Qué relación tiene exactamente con Tenma?
Eva Heinemann, I don't know who you are,
Eva Heinemann, no sé quién es usted,
but I'm going to help Tenma.
pero yo voy a ayudar a Tenma.
I don't want you tagging along if you're just here for your enjoyment.
No quiero que me acompañe si solo viene a divertirse.
Eva Heinemann…
Eva Heinemann.
Heinemann?
¿Heinemann?
Wait! Don't tell me
Espere, ¡no me diga!
you're the daughter of Director Heinemann who was murdered
Es la hija de Heinemann,
Dr. Tenma…
El doctor Tenma
He's the man who destroyed my life.
es el hombre que me arruinó la vida.
But you know what? I'm the only one who can save him.
¿Sabe qué? Yo soy la única que puede salvarlo.
I saw it.
Yo lo vi.
Saw what?
¿El qué?
A decision has been made to extradite Kenzo Tenma
Se ha decidido que la extradición de Tenma
to Germany in the next day or two from where he was arrested in Prague.
se llevará a cabo en uno o dos días desde el lugar donde lo arrestaron.
It's presumed that he'll be sent to Düsseldorf where his crimes began.
Entiendo que lo llevarán a Düsseldorf, donde comenzaron los crímenes.
After he's questioned,
Después de interrogarlo…
Impossible. That's just not possible.
Imposible. No puede ser.
This man… This doctor couldn't do those things.
Ese médico no pudo hacer esas cosas.
This is Dr. Tenma.
El doctor Tenma.
Suk, you owe him your life.
Suk, le debe la vida.
He's the doctor who gave you first aid.
Él le dio los primeros auxilios.
Dr. Tenma's also been accused of crimes he never committed.
También le acusan de crímenes que nunca llevó a cabo.
He's in the same situation as you.
Los dos están en la misma situación.
I owe him my life, but he's in the same situation as me.
Le debo mi vida, pero estamos en la misma situación.
You're a detective, right?
Usted es policía, ¿no?
As a detective, you must calmly dissect and investigate everything.
Como policía, debe analizarlo con calma e investigarlo todo.
If you don't want to be betrayed anymore…
Si no quiere que lo traicionen otra vez,
Then suspect the person you least want to suspect.
tenga cuidado con la persona menos sospechosa.
I have to go.
Tengo que irme.
I have to get to Prague Police Station and speak with Dr. Tenma.
Tengo que llegar a la comisaría para hablar con el doctor Tenma.
We've been looking for you, Suk.
Estábamos buscándole, Suk.
Detective Blazek. Detective Stransky. I didn't--
Detective Blazek, detective Stransky.
You don't have to run anymore.
Ya puede dejar de huir.
You've been through a heck of a lot.
Ha pasado por muchas cosas,
But you've been cleared now.
pero ya está limpio.
We received a letter at the station.
- Ha llegado una carta a comisaría. - Aquí tiene una copia.
A letter?
¿Una carta?
It's a confession containing details
Es una confesión con detalles que solo el asesino podría conocer.
You've been cleared of all suspicion.
Queda absuelto de toda sospecha.
Who wrote that letter?
¿De quién es la carta?
A guy named Grimmer.
Un hombre llamado Grimmer.
What?
¿Qué?
He's been placed on the most wanted list as a suspect.
Lo han incluido en la lista de los más buscados.
Hey! Wait a minute!
Esperen un momento.
There's no need to worry anymore, Suk.
Ya no tiene de qué preocuparse, Suk.
This clears up all the cases, the beating death of Inspector Zeman,
Esto lo aclara todo: la muerte del inspector Zeman,
the poisoning of the commissioner, and the shooting
el envenenamiento del comisario
of the two task force members.
y los disparos al cuerpo especial.
Where the heck have you been, Lunge?
¿Dónde se ha metido, Lunge?
I've called you several times!
Le he llamado varias veces.
Sorry, Chief. I was doing some sightseeing.
Lo siento, jefe. Estaba haciendo turismo.
What's your problem? Don't play dumb with me!
¿Qué te pasa? Déjate de tonterías.
"Play dumb"? What do you mean?
¿Tonterías? ¿A qué se refiere?
I've had enough of this! Don't tell me you haven't seen the news!
¡Basta! No me diga que no ha visto las noticias.
JAPANESE DOCTOR CAPTURED IN PRAGUE
MÉDICO JAPONÉS DETENIDO EN PRAGA
Do you mean about the arrest of Dr. Tenma?
¿Lo del arresto del doctor Tenma?
Congratulations, Lunge.
Enhorabuena, Lunge.
What?
¿Eh?
You knew Tenma was hiding in Prague, didn't you?
Usted sabía que se escondía en Praga, ¿no?
Well done, Lunge. Your persistence in this investigation has paid off at last.
Bien hecho, Lunge. Su persistencia en el caso ha dado frutos.
Our people here at BKA have contacted the Czech Police and arranged things.
Los de Investigación Criminal ya han hablado con la policía checa
Tenma will be transported to Düsseldorf tomorrow afternoon.
Mañana por la tarde llevarán a Tenma a Düsseldorf.
Since you're in charge of this case,
Como el caso es suyo, quiero que se encargue usted del traslado.
I've really got to hand it to you, Lunge. Congratulations.
Tiene mis respetos, Lunge. Enhorabuena.
Send someone else to do it.
Mande a otra persona.
Huh?
¿Eh?
Prague is a beautiful city.
Praga es muy bonita.
What?
¿Qué?
Hey, Lunge! What the heck's gotten into you? Hey!
¡Lunge! ¿Qué narices le pasa? ¡Oiga!
Let me speak with Dr. Tenma!
Quiero hablar con el doctor Tenma.
I've already told you! You can't speak with him!
Ya le he dicho que no puede hablar con él.
Then tell me why! I thought this was a democratic country!
Pero ¿por qué? ¡Creía que esto era una democracia!
Tenma's going to be extradited to Germany.
Van a trasladarlo a Alemania.
Just let me see him for a moment before then!
Déjenme verlo solo un momento.
Sounds like this was a waste of time.
Qué pérdida de tiempo.
After all the effort we spent getting to Prague.
Después de haber venido a Praga y todo.
I'm begging you! Just a brief minute!
Se lo suplico. Solo un minuto.
Get out here.
Fuera.
Come this way.
Por aquí.
When we interrogate people, who do you think
En un interrogatorio, ¿cuál cree usted que es la parte más complicada?
The people whose expression never changes no matter what we say.
La gente que tiene la misma expresión todo el rato.
The people who don't say a word.
La gente que no dice nada.
They're the hardest kind.
Eso son los más complicados.
"The Monster's Love Letter to the Beauty."
"La carta del monstruo a la bella".
It's like a draft of a novel.
Parece el borrador de una novela.
"I've always watched you."
"Siempre te he observado.
"I've watched you so I could devour all of you."
Te observaba para poder cometer entera,
"But everything about you has devoured me instead."
aunque al final toda tú has terminado devorándome a mí.
"As I was falling to pieces, how did I appear to you?"
A medida que me hacía añicos, ¿qué te parecía yo?
"As I fell to pieces, you gave me something."
Me hacía añicos y tú me diste algo.
"You left me with beautiful gems,
Me dejaste con tus piedras preciosas:
those twins who seem to have eternal life."
dos gemelos que parecen ser inmortales.
"The greatest crime is to steal someone's name."
El crimen más grande es robarle el nombre a otra persona.
"Let's get your name back."
Vamos a devolverte tu nombre.
"I'll give you your name back."
Yo te devolveré el mío.
"Your name is Anna."
Tu nombre es Anna.
"Now, I am simply sad."
Ahora estoy triste".
It exists.
Existe.
Many people died in that room.
Mucha gente murió en esa sala.
And then, a horrific monster was born.
Y entonces, nació un monstruo terrible.